<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<vignette name="Abstractions" package="Max">
  <h1>
    Getting Started with afterglow-max
  </h1>
  <p>
    As noted on the <a
    href="https://github.com/brunchboy/afterglow-max#installation">project
    page</a>, you need to have the Open Lighting Architecture
    installed for afterglow to work, and an OLA universe created for
    your show to work with. Make sure you have followed those
    instructions before trying to get real things to happen with your
    afterglow-max objects.
  </p>
  <p>
    Once you have, you can start experimenting with them, seeing how
    they respond to messages, and even watching the responses of
    Afterglow's embedded <a
    href="https://github.com/brunchboy/afterglow/blob/master/doc/README.adoc#the-embedded-web-interface">web
    interface</a>, and the DMX values being sent to OLA on its own <a
    href="http://localhost:9090/new/">web UI</a>.
  </p>
  <p>
    In order to get your own light show going with the fixtures you
    actually have, you will need to find or create appropriate fixture
    definitions, and configure your own show to patch them at the
    right DMX addresses and physical locations and orientations. This
    guide will help you do that.
  </p>
  <br />
  <bluebox>
    <h2>
      Fixture Definitions
    </h2>
    In order to control a piece of lighting equipment, Afterglow needs
    to know the features it has available, and the channels and
    control values which select and operate those features. This
    information is organized into <i>fixture definitions</i>. Over
    time, more and more of these will be built into the base Afterglow
    distribution, but at the moment there are very few, so you are
    likely going to need to create your own, or ask for help doing so.
    <br/>
    <br/>

    The <a
    href="https://github.com/brunchboy/afterglow/blob/master/doc/fixture_definitions.adoc#fixture-definitions">Fixture
    Definitions</a> page on the main Afterglow project site explains
    how to examine and create fixture definitions, so that is where to
    start. Check whether your particular fixtures happen to be already
    supported, and, if not, read how to write new definitions for
    them.
    <br/>
    <br/>

    As a Max user, however, you may find that task more challenging
    than it is for people who have adopted Afterglow from a more
    traditional programming background. If so, you are very much
    encouraged to ask for help on the Afterglow <a
    href="https://github.com/brunchboy/afterglow/wiki/Questions">wiki</a>.
    Especially at this very early stage, the developer is eager to
    help early adopters find success with Afterglow, because that will
    help it grow into a thriving ecosystem. If you can provide a link
    to the documentation of your fixture, someone with practice in
    writing definitions should be able to whip one up for you fairly
    quickly. (Also, if you are skilled at creating Max patches, then
    even though Clojure is a textual rather than graphical
    environment, you do have an advantage over people who come from
    more common imperative programming languages, since both Max and
    Clojure take a functional approach.)
    <br/>
    <br/>

    If all else fails you can also contact the <a
    href="mailto:james@deepsymmetry.org">author</a> directly, although
    starting with the wiki gives others a chance to benefit from your
    questions in the future.
    <br/>
    <br/>

    Whether you are writing your own definitions, or incorporating one
    that someone created for you, the fastest way to get them into
    afterglow-max (rather than waiting for a future release to include
    them), is to add them to the file
    <b>afterglow-max/java-classes/fixtures.clj</b> in your Max
    Packages directory where you installed afterglow-max. (This
    assumes that you left the afterglow-max package folder name the
    same as it was when you downloaded it. If you changed it, find the
    file inside whatever you renamed the package.) This file gets
    loaded by the <b>init.clj</b> file when afterglow-max is starting
    up, so your fixture definitions will be available for use within
    your show, as described below.
    <br/>
    <br/>

    To avoid having to quit and relaunch Max every time you want to
    reload your fixture definitions, you can use the <b>reload-init</b> (top)
    message button in this <openfilelink
    filename="afterglow.eval.example.maxpat">Eval
    Example</openfilelink>. It also has suggestions about other, even
    more convenient ways of working with Clojure code from inside Max.
  </bluebox>
  <br />
  <p>
    Once you have the fixture definitions in place, you need to patch
    them into a show, telling Afterglow the DMX addresses they are
    listening on, and their physical locations.
  </p>
  <bluebox>
    <h2>
      Patching a Show
    </h2>

    The function <b>use-demo-show</b> inside <b>init.clj</b> is an
    example of how to do this. Essentially, you will call <a
    href="http://deepsymmetry.org/afterglow/doc/afterglow.show.html#var-patch-fixture.21">show/patch-fixture!</a>
    once for each lighting fixture that you have hooked up to your DMX
    interface, telling Afterglow the keyword you want to assign that
    fixture, the fixture definition that explains how to control it,
    the universe within your show that it is attached to (even if
    there is only one universe), the DMX address that it is listening
    to, and the physical location and orientation within <a
    href="https://github.com/brunchboy/afterglow/blob/master/doc/show_space.adoc#show-space">show
    space</a> that you have hung the light.
    <br/>
    <br/>

    Again, you can avoid having to quit and relaunch Max every time
    you want to reload your init file as you work on setting up your
    show, by using the <b>reload-init</b> (top) message button in this
    <openfilelink filename="afterglow.eval.example.maxpat">Eval
    Example</openfilelink>, or an actual Clojure development
    environment connected to afterglow-max via nrepl.
  </bluebox>
  <br />
  <p>
    Then you will want some cues that are specific to your actual
    fixtures.
  </p>
  <bluebox>
    <h2>
      Creating Cues
    </h2>
    <p>
      The <a
      href="http://deepsymmetry.org/afterglow/doc/afterglow.examples.html#var-make-cues">make-cues</a>
      function in Afterglow's examples namespace creates all the cues
      you have seen if you looked at the demo show in the web
      interface (or on an Ableton Push controller). You will want to
      look at its source code as an example for how to create cues
      that are tailored to the lights you actually have, and which are
      arranged, labeled, and colored in a way that makes sense to you.
    </p>
    <p>
      Getting familiar with the Afterglow documentation about <a
      href="https://github.com/brunchboy/afterglow/blob/master/doc/cues.adoc#cues">Cues</a>
      and <a
      href="https://github.com/brunchboy/afterglow/blob/master/doc/effects.adoc#effects">Effects</a>
      will be extremely helpful at this stage.
    </p>
    <p>
      Remember that you can avoid having to quit and relaunch Max
      every time you want to reload your init file as you work on
      setting up your cues, with the help of the <b>reload-init</b>
      (top) message button in this <openfilelink
      filename="afterglow.eval.example.maxpat">Eval
      Example</openfilelink>, or an actual Clojure development
      environment connected to afterglow-max via nrepl.
    </p>
  </bluebox>
  <p>
    And, finally...
  </p>
  <bluebox>
    <h2>
      Creating Your Own Effects
    </h2>
    <p>
      Once you have a set of cues that control your actual lights, you
      can be really productive with Afterglow. You can control those
      cues with either a physical controller, the built in Web
      interface, or the <openfilelink
      filename="afterglow.max.Cue.maxhelp">afterglow.max.Cue</openfilelink>
      Max object. But that is just where the fun begins! You can
      combine the Cue object with an <openfilelink
      filename="afterglow.max.NextFrame.maxhelp">afterglow.max.NextFrame</openfilelink>
      object to tweak the way the cue looks on a frame-by-frame basis
      in response to the progression of musical time, or in response
      to some sort of audio processing you are doing within Max, or to
      tie into a Vizzie visualization... your imagination is the
      limit.
    </p>
    <p>
      And once you feel ready to dig deeper, you can even use the full
      power of the Clojure language to create brand new effects that
      go beyond the ones <a
      href="https://github.com/brunchboy/afterglow/blob/master/doc/effects.adoc#effects">built
      in</a> to Afterglow. The entire purpose of Afterglow is to make
      that kind of extension and customization as easy as possible, to
      be responsive enough that you can even do that in the middle of
      a performance. It is a live-coding environment for light shows.
    </p>
    <p>
      Have fun with it!
    </p>
  </bluebox>
  <p>
    Don’t forget to contribute your fixture definitions and effects to
    the Afterglow community! If you are confident that you have fully
    mapped out the functions of a fixture, please make a <a
    href="https://github.com/brunchboy/afterglow/pulls">pull
    request</a> to include it in afterglow, either within the existing
    namespace for its manufacturer, or creating a new namespace for a
    new manufacturer. Similarly, if you have created an awesome new
    kind of effect, please consider a pull request to add it somewhere
    within the effects namespace hierarchy. And if you are just
    tinkering with something new and experimental, please post about
    it on the <a
    href="https://github.com/brunchboy/afterglow/wiki">wiki</a>!
  </p>
</vignette>
