<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="./_c74_ref.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<c74object name="afterglow.max.Metro" module="max" category="afterglow-max, DMX Light Shows">
  <digest>
    Adjust and query an Afterglow Metronome
  </digest>
	
  <description>
    Allows you to set the tempo and other parameters of a <a
    href="https://github.com/brunchboy/afterglow/blob/master/doc/metronomes.adoc#metronomes">Metronome</a>
    object (either the default show metronome, or one stored in a
    named show variable).
    <br/>
    <br/>

    The left inlet controls the metronome's tempo, in terms of beats
    per minute. A <m>float</m> or <m>int</m> directly sets the BPM
    value, while a series of <m>tap</m> messages can establish a BPM
    by their actual timing. Sending a <m>bang</m> message outputs the
    current BPM to the first outlet (and causes all other outlets to
    send their timing information as well), without changing it. Note
    that if the metronome is currently synchronized with a tempo
    source within Afterglow (such as MIDI clock or Pioneer Pro DJ
    Link), attempts to alter its BPM via this inlet will be ignored.
    <br/>
    <br/>

    The second inlet controls the current phrase number being counted
    by the metronome. Sending an <m>int</m> message sets the phrase
    number directly. Sending a <m>tap</m> message indicates that a
    phrase is starting right now, and the nearest phrase boundary will
    be moved so that it has just started. A <m>bang</m> message
    outputs the current phrase to the second outlet (and causes all
    other outlets to send their timing information as well), without
    changing it.
    <br/>
    <br/>

    The third inlet controls the current bar within the phrase being
    counted by the metronome. Sending an <m>int</m> message sets the
    bar number directly. Sending a <m>tap</m> message indicates that a
    bar is starting right now, and the nearest bar boundary will be
    moved so that it has just started. A <m>bang</m> message outputs
    the current bar to the third outlet (and cause all other outlets
    to send their timing information as well), without changing it.
    <br/>
    <br/>

    The right inlet controls the current beat within the bar being
    counted by the metronome. Sending an <m>int</m> message sets the
    beat number directly. Sending a <m>tap</m> message indicates that
    a beat is starting right now, and the nearest beat boundary will
    be moved so that it has just started. A <m>bang</m> message
    outputs the current beat to the fourth outlet (and causes all
    other outlets to send their timing information as well), without
    changing it. Note that if the metronome is currently synchronized
    with a beat grid within Afterglow (such as Pioneer Pro DJ Link),
    attempts to move the beat starting time via this inlet will be
    ignored.
    <br/>
    <br/>

    The right outlet sends a <m>list</m> containing the <i>phases</i>
    that have been reached within the phrase, bar, and beat. Phases
    are <m>float</m> values that range from 0.0, at the very start of
    the interval, approaching (but never quite reaching) 1.0, as the
    next interval approaches. Once the next beat, bar, or phrase
    starts, of course, the phase returns to zero. Phases are very
    useful for generating effects; see the <openfilelink
    filename="afterglow.max.NextFrame.maxhelp">NextFrame</openfilelink>
    Help for an example. These phases will be sent whenever any inlet
    receives a <m>bang</m>.
    <br/>
    <br/>

    If an argument is given, it is used as the name of a show variable
    in which a Metronome will be looked up. With no argument, the
    show's default metronome is used.
  </description>
	
  <!--METADATA-->
  <metadatalist>
    <metadata name="author">James Elliott, Deep Symmetry, LLC</metadata>
    <metadata name="tag">DeepSymmetry</metadata>
    <metadata name="tag">DMX</metadata>
    <metadata name="tag">mxj</metadata>
    <metadata name="tag">Light Shows</metadata>
  </metadatalist>
	
  <!--INLETS-->
  <inletlist>
    <inlet id="0" type="message">
      <digest>int, float: set BPM; tap: learn BPM; bang: send state</digest>
    </inlet>
    <inlet id="1" type="message">
      <digest>int: set phrase; tap: start phrase; bang: send state</digest>
    </inlet>
    <inlet id="2" type="message">
      <digest>int: set bar; tap: start bar; bang: send state</digest>
    </inlet>
    <inlet id="3" type="message">
      <digest>int: set beat; tap: start beat; bang: send state</digest>
    </inlet>
  </inletlist>

  <!--OUTLETS-->
  <outletlist>
    <outlet id="0" type="float">
      <digest>current BPM</digest>
    </outlet>
    <outlet id="1" type="int">
      <digest>current phrase number</digest>
    </outlet>
    <outlet id="2" type="int">
      <digest>current bar within phrase</digest>
    </outlet>
    <outlet id="3" type="int">
      <digest>current beat within bar</digest>
    </outlet>
    <outlet id="4" type="list">
      <digest>phrase phase, bar phase, beat phase</digest>
    </outlet>
  </outletlist>
	
  <!--ARGUMENTS-->
  <objarglist>
    <objarg name="variable" optional="1" type="String">
      <digest>The name of a variable within the show containing the
      metronome. If omitted, use the default metronome of the
      show.</digest>
    </objarg>
  </objarglist>
	
  <!--MESSAGES-->
  <methodlist>
    <method name="bang">
      <arglist />
      <digest>
        Send current state
      </digest>
      <description>
        Regardless of the inlet to which it is sent, causes all
        outlets to send current timing information.
      </description>
    </method>
    <method name="float">
      <arglist>
	<arg name="new-value" optional="0" type="float" />
      </arglist>
      <digest>
        Set current BPM in first inlet
      </digest>
      <description>
	Sets the current tempo in beats per minute when set to the
        first inlet. If the metronome is synchronized to an external
        tempo source, attempts to set the BPM will be ignored. Other
        inlets only respond to <m>int</m> messages, so <m>float</m>
        values sent to them will be truncated to integers and sent
        that way.
      </description>
    </method>
    <method name="int">
      <arglist>
	<arg name="new-value" optional="0" type="int" />
      </arglist>
      <digest>
        Set current value, meaning depends on inlet
      </digest>
      <description>
	Sets the value of the corresponding metronome parameter. Each
        inlet interprets it appropriately; see the inlet descriptions
        for details. If the metronome is synchronized to an external
        tempo source, attempts to set the BPM will be ignored.
      </description>
    </method>
    <method name="tap">
      <arglist />
      <digest>
	Indicate timing, meaning depends on inlet
      </digest>
      <description>
        Provides a tap-tempo mechanism for adjusting the tempo based
        on external timing signals when sent to the first inlet. For
        the other inlets, indicates that the associated interval (a
        phrase, bar, or beat) has just started, so the nearest
        boundary will be moved to start now. If the metronome is
        currently synchronized with a tempo source or beat grid within
        Afterglow (such as MIDI clock or Pioneer Pro DJ Link), taps on
        some inlets will be ignored, as described in their
        documentation.
      </description>
    </method>
  </methodlist>
	
  <!--SEEALSO-->
  <seealsolist>
    <seealso name="afterglow.max.Cue"/>
    <seealso name="afterglow.max.Eval"/>
    <seealso name="afterglow.max.NextFrame"/>
    <seealso name="afterglow.max.Var"/>
  </seealsolist>
</c74object>
